<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A packe of Spanish lyes sent abroad in the vvorld: first printed in Spaine in the Spanish tongue, and translated out of the originall. Now ripped vp, vnfolded, and by iust examination condemned, as conteyning false, corrupt, and detestable wares, worthy to be damned and burned.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23011</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117693</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852904</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852904</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18259</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12691)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18259)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 332:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A packe of Spanish lyes sent abroad in the vvorld: first printed in Spaine in the Spanish tongue, and translated out of the originall. Now ripped vp, vnfolded, and by iust examination condemned, as conteyning false, corrupt, and detestable wares, worthy to be damned and burned.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the deputies of Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of and reply to an untraced Spanish original printed in Seville.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Armada, 1588 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18259:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18259:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PACKE OF SPANISH LYES, SENT ABROAD IN THE WORLD: FIRST printed in SPAINE in the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
tongue, and tranſlated out of the <hi>Originall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ripped vp, vnfolded, and by iuſt <hi>exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation condemned, as conteyning falſe,
corrupt, and detestable wares, worthy to be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and burned.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 5. VERS. 6.</bibl>
               <p>Thou ſhalt deſtroy them that ſpeake lyes, the Lord wil abhorre the bloodie and deceitfull
man.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London by the Deputies</hi> of Chriſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes
moſt excellent Maieſtie. 1588.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="original" type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:18259:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18259:2"/>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A Packe of SPA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NISH lyes. <hi>From Spaine.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE true relation of the ſucces of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like armye againſt their enemies, by
letters of the Poſt maſter of <hi>Logrono</hi> of the iiii. of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, and by letters from
<hi>Roan</hi> of the one &amp; thirtieth of Auguſt, <hi>(<hi rend="sup">a</hi>)</hi> and by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from
<hi>Paris</hi> of the Kings Embaſſadour there: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee declareth the impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment of
<hi>Francis Drake,</hi> and other great Nobles of Englande, and howe the <hi>Queene</hi> is in the
fielde with an armie, <hi>(<hi rend="sup">b</hi>)</hi> and of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>mutinie</hi> which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the
Queenes army,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18259:3"/> with the ſucceſſe of the ſaid Catholike armie ſince they entred in the
<hi>Groyne,</hi> till they came on the coaſt of England, with two ballets compounded by
<hi>Chriſtouer Brauo,</hi> a <hi>(<hi rend="sup">c</hi>)</hi> blinde man of <hi>Cordowa,</hi> Printed with lycence
by <hi>Gabriel Ramos Beiarano</hi> Printer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:18259:3"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A Packe of Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh lies. <hi>From Spaine.</hi>
                  </hi> By a letter of <hi>Diego
Peres,</hi> chiefe Poſtmaſter of <hi>Logrono,</hi> dated the ſecond of September.
<hi>1588.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="2">2 THe newes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande is confirmed here, by a letter of the Gouernour of <hi>Roan.</hi>
He writeth he hath in his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the chiefe Pilot of <hi>cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Drake,</hi> and that hee knoweth
that all the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh armie remained ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen, hauing ſunke <hi>two and twentie ſhippes,
and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken fourtie, (<hi rend="sup">d</hi>)</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned <hi>Francis Drake,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing giuen them chaſe
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as hie as <hi>(<hi rend="sup">e</hi>) Abſpurge,</hi> and ſlaine many by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſword, and likewiſe
ſayeth that there was found in <hi>captaine Drakes</hi> ſhippe, a piece of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of fiue
and twentie foote long, which diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged a ſhotte of a hundreth weight at once, made of
purpoſe, with one onely ſhot to ſinke our <hi>Spaniſh Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,</hi> and it pleaſed God
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhee was ſomewhat
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18259:4"/> battered, yet was ſhe repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe, and ouerthrewe the Engliſh
armie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18259:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A Packe of Spaniſh lies. <hi>From Spaine.</hi>
                  </hi> Copie of a letter that <hi>Iohn
Gamarra</hi> wrote from <hi>Roan</hi> the xxxi. of Auguſt of the ſame yeere.</head>
               <p n="3">3 THe Engliſh haue loſt aboue <hi>xl. ſhips</hi> in one encounter, where they coulde
not flie, which was in <hi>(<hi rend="sup">f</hi>) Luxaten</hi> a Hauen in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to the which place,
ſince the departure of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> armies fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Calleis,</hi> the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh armie
folowed, and ſuppoſing they went to take that Hauen, they got be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ours to defend the
entrance: we ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them ſo neere the Engliſh fleete, and that they coulde not retire, as
they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes did, when they pleaſed, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Hauens, they ſet vpon them ſo
vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly, that they ſunke <hi>xx. of their ſhips,</hi> and they tooke <hi>xxvi. whole and
ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi> and the reſt ſeeing their deſtruction, fled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with great loſſe of men,
and their ſhips very much battered, &amp; with this (they ſay) the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> armie
tooke the Hauen, where they are very well lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, as euery one affirmeth, and ſo the newes is
here: I pray God giue them good ſucceſſe: wee vnderſtande by the Poſt come from
<hi>Calleis,</hi> that in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it is forbidden vppon paine of death and loſſe of goods, that
no body doe write newes from thence to any place: which confirmeth the newes aboue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:18259:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A Packe of Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh lies. <hi>From Spaine.</hi>
                  </hi> Coppie of a Letter that <hi>Pedro
de Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua</hi> did write from <hi>Roan</hi> the firſt of September of the ſame yeere.</head>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>I</hi> Do not write newes of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> armie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are
diuers, and woulde gladly write the very trueth. Nowe by the newes which runneth from diuers
places, as <hi>Calleis, Deepe,</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande,</hi> and preſumptions from England, &amp;
other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, it is holden for certaine, that they haue fought with the Engliſh, &amp; broken
their heads, hauing ſunke many of their ſhips, and taken o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp; the reſt which they
ſay were xxvii. ſhips, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned very much battered to the Riuer of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don, which are all
thoſe that coulde eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape: There goeth with this Poſt another Poſt of <hi>Iorge Seguin</hi>
of <hi>Calles,</hi> which ſaith that certaine Maſters and Mariners of <hi>Zeland,</hi> did
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme to the Gouernours of <hi>Calleis, Mounſier de Gorden,</hi> that our fleete is in a Hauen

<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18259:5"/> or Riuer in <hi>Scotland</hi> called <hi>(e) Trifla,</hi> where they ſay there
may ride two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Ships: this is that which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly is currant here.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Packe of Spaniſh lies. <hi>From Spaine.</hi>
                  </hi> Aduiſe from London, which the
Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour of our ſoueraigne Lord the King reſident in <hi>Paris,</hi> had from
thence.</head>
               <p n="5">5 BY newes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>London</hi> of the xxvi. of Auguſt, it is knowen for moſt certaine
from perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Queenes Admiral general was arriued in the riuer of
<hi>London,</hi> with xxv. ſhips onely without his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral ſhip, <hi>(<hi rend="sup">h</hi>)</hi> which was taken
by our Admiral <hi>Saint Iohn,</hi> &amp; it is well knowen in <hi>Enga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ld,</hi> that to hide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
loſſe of their Admiral ſhip, they ſay he put himſelfe in a ſmaller ſhip y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better to
folow our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie: &amp; it is knowen for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſaued him ſelf in a boat when he
loſt his ſhip. That <hi>Drake</hi> for certaintie is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſlain. The ſame is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of <hi>Holland,</hi> by a Pinnaſſe of theirs. And
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18259:6"/> from <hi>Auſterland,</hi> that the Queene commanded vpon paine of death, that
no body ſhoulde ſpeake of her fleete, and that there was great ſorow in thoſe parts of
Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and that the Queene had in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> field thirty thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d raw ſouldiers, betwixt
<hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi> &amp; <hi>Margate,</hi> &amp; that (<hi rend="sup">i</hi>) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks vnderſtanding that al
their fleete was diſperſed, moued a certaine mutinie, which forced the Queene to go herſelfe
into the fielde, and for certain it is knowen that there is not brought in to England, neither
ſhip nor boate of ours, more then the ſhip of <hi>Don Pedro valdez,</hi> &amp; that our fleete
was gone in to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and arriued in a Hauen called <hi>(<hi rend="sup">k</hi>) Trapena Euxaten.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Packe of Spaniſh lies. <hi>From Spaine.</hi>
                  </hi> By a letter of the chiefe Poſt
maſter of <hi>Burdeux,</hi> written to the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour, the <hi>2.</hi> of
Sept. <hi>1588.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="6">6 AFter that I had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten this, here is arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a <hi>Scottiſhman,</hi> which ſaith
that all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Spaniſh</hi> fleete
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18259:6"/> is arriued in <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp; that the <hi>Scottiſhmen</hi> haue
taken armes againſt the Engliſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Packe of Spaniſh lies. <hi>From Spayne.</hi>
                  </hi> Relation of that which hath
paſſed till this day, the fifth of September <hi>1588.</hi> till three of the clocke in the
after noone, knowen by the relations and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe come to his Maieſtie from the happie fleete,
whereof is Generall the <hi>Duke of Medina,</hi> in the conqueſt of England.</head>
               <p n="7">7 THat vpon the thirtieth of Iuly, without ſeeing any ſayle of the enemies in the
ſea, hee came to the Channell, ſixe leagues from <hi>Plim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth:</hi> where vnderſtanding the
ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were, hee gathered together and ſet in order all the fleete: and ſayling the firſt
of Auguſt, there was diſcouered ſome ſayles of the enemies, the which the ſecond day were
nombred to bee lx. ſaile, of which the Duke tooke the wind, &amp; paſſed without any fight,
although he preſented y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to them, howbeit they began to ſhoot at the Rereward: but the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18259:7"/> Duke in the Galleon <hi>S. Martin,</hi> ſet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prow of his ſhip againſt
the biggeſt of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which being ſuccoured by twenty others, fled away: of this
fight and firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, there was ſunke three <hi>Galeaſſes,</hi> &amp; foure mighty
<hi>Galeons</hi> of the Queenes: there was burnt of ours by negligence of a Gunner, the Admiral of
<hi>Oquendo,</hi> &amp; the enemies tooke the chiefe ſhip of <hi>Don Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro Valdez,</hi> which
being entangled with others vnder his charge: was left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out tackle, and ſo neere the enemies,
that ſhe coulde not be ſuccoured by others.</p>
               <p>With this, our fleete ſeeing that the enemie in euery point did flie from gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing battell,
they ſailed with ſome calme weather, &amp; the enemies after them, ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting alwayes at the
Rereward, vntil the ſeuenth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our fleet ancored in the Roade of <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> betwixt
<hi>Calleis</hi> &amp; <hi>Bollin,</hi> nine leagues from <hi>Dunkerke,</hi> &amp; the enemies did
the like, the neereſt they could to Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</p>
               <p>The night being approched, the enemies got vp their ankers, to get the wind, and not to ſuffer
our ſhippes to goe out of the Roade to ſea, becauſe they had trimmed viii. ſhips of fire,
which with the corrent of the water, ſhould haue put them ſelues amongſt our ſhips, to haue
burnt them. But my Lord the Duke, foreſeeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, preuented them, with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement that
the ſhippes that were neereſt, ſhould cut their Cables, &amp; to take vp the others with a
readineſſe vncredible: and with this the enemies pretence was hindered,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18259:7"/> and ſo got the ſea moſt brauely, and with ſuch good fortune, that if he
had not done it, our armie ſhould haue ben in euil caſe, for in the very place which we left,
there was ſhotte off by them, out of thoſe fierie ſhips, ſuch fires, &amp; other engins,
that were ſufficient to burne the Sea, much more, ſhips which are made of wood and pitch.</p>
               <p>In this departure, the Captaine of the Galeaſſes had a great miſchance: for get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp
her Anker, a Cable fel foule of her Helme, that ſhe could not follow the reſt, which cauſed
one of her ſides to lie ſo hie, that her ordinance could not play, and ſo xxv. Pinaſes came
and battered her, and withall this, if the mariners, ſouldiers, &amp; rowers that were in her,
had not caſt themſelues into the ſea, it is holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that <hi>(m) Don Hugo de
Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cada</hi> had defended her, as he did vntil ſhe came into <hi>Calleis,</hi> where at the
entrance thereof, he was killed of two Caliuer ſhot, the people on ſhore defended the
Galeaſſe, &amp; all that was in her, and deliuered the ſame to our Soueraigne Lord the Kings
miniſters.</p>
               <p>At this time, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Duke had a very franke wind, &amp; the like had the Queenes Fleete: and ſo
they both paſſed by the ſight of <hi>Du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerke,</hi> inſomuch as they on land knew the
Gallion <hi>S. Martin,</hi> and others that went fighting with the Engliſh armie, and in this
order they went till the twelfth.</p>
               <p>Afterwards they write, that there came into <hi>Calleis</hi> a ſhip, which ſaith, that the
<hi>(n)</hi> xii. day they did ſee the two Fleetes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18259:8"/> in fight: an other which came af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes, ſaid hee had ſeene ſome
ſhips ſpoiled and torne, &amp; from them they threw out <hi>(o)</hi> their baggage which they
ſaued in boats, which argueth, they were ſhips of the enemies, for that our men had no place to
ſaue them ſelues, nor there were none of them arriued into <hi>Fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders,</hi> which was their
place of returne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A Packe of Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh lies. <hi>From Spaine.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="8">8 OVt of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande was aduiſe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xiii. arriued fifteene of the Queens
ſhips, and they ſayd that the <hi>Galleon Saint Martin,</hi> wherin my Lorde the <hi>Duke</hi>
is, (whome God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue) had encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with <hi>Drake,</hi> &amp; had grapled his ſhip,
&amp; captiued his Perſon, and other Noble Engliſh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and taken other fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene ſhips,
beſide others y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed, &amp; the <hi>Duke</hi> with his fleete, fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18259:8"/> his way to <hi>Scotland,</hi> becauſe the winde was not come about.</p>
               <p>With theſe news, his Maieſtie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth verie much contented, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to be
ſent to the Empreſſe, by the hands of <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſco Ydiaquez,</hi> his Secretarie of
eſtate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="colophon">
               <p>IMPRINTED in SEVIL in the <hi>houſe of</hi> Coſmo de la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra <hi>Printer of Bookes, by lycence
of the</hi> Counte <hi>of</hi> Orgaz, <hi>Aſſiſtant in</hi> SEVIL.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="epigraph">
               <q>
                  <bibl>IOAN. 8.44.</bibl>
                  <p>Ye are of your father the Deuil, and the luſtes of your father ye will doe: hee hath bene a
murtherer from the beginning, and aboade not in the trueth, becauſe there is no trueth in him.
When hee ſpeaketh a lye, then ſpeaketh hee of his owne: for hee is a lyer and the father
thereof.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="original" type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:18259:2"/>
            <head>A condemnation of <hi>the SPANISH lies.</hi> From England.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is wel knowen to all the worlde, how falſe all this relation is, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
falſly colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Letters remembred, or els both the poſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of <hi>Logrono,</hi>
and the writers from <hi>Roan</hi> ought to be waged as Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencers for the deuill the father
of lyes, whom they haue herein truely ſerued: and if they ſo continue in mayntenance thereof
againſt the knowen trueth, their damnation is certaine, and hell is open for them.</p>
               <p>(<hi rend="sup">a</hi>) The Letters from the kings Ambaſſadour, whoſe name is <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doza,</hi> agreeable to
their Maſters name, being the reporter of <hi>menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cià mendaciſſima,</hi> &amp;
conſidering that hee hath written that <hi>Francis Drake</hi> is impriſoned, and many Nobles of
England, if <hi>Mendoza</hi> will ſtand to his Letters, ſo as he would gage, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18259:3"/> by his hande writing aſſure but his worſt Iennet and his belles, he
ſhall be anſwered for the ſaid Sir <hi>Francis Drakes</hi> perſon, or any Nobleman,
gentleman, or page ſo taken in the fight betweene the two Armies, for the ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſom of euery of
the ſaid priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners 40000. Crownes in the Royal Eſchange of London. But the truth is, Sir
<hi>Francis Drake</hi> was ſo farre off to be a priſoner, that hee was the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker: for hee
tooke <hi>Pedro de Valdez,</hi> and 400. moe Spaniſh priſoners at one time. And to proue this
to be true, <hi>Mendoza</hi> ſhall haue if hee will require it, <hi>Pedro de Valdez</hi> owne
hand to ſhewe, that he is priſoner to Sir <hi>Francis Drake,</hi> and 400. moe taken with him,
and not one Engliſh man taken in that ſeruice.</p>
               <p>(<hi rend="sup">b</hi>) It is ſo falſe that there was any <hi>mutinie</hi> in the Q. Armie, that ſhee her
ſelfe was there, with the greateſt honour, loue, and applauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, that coulde be
imagined for a Lady and a Queene. She rode rounde about her Armie, and paſſed through euery
part thereof, to their ineſtimable comfort: ſhee lodged and did eate in the Campe, as quietly
as euer ſhe did in her owne chamber. In the Armie was neuer any fray or diſcord: exerciſe of
Armes was dayly vſed and ſhewed before her, to her great honour: yea, and with an vniuerſall
extolling of Gods Name euery day Morning and Euening, in loude prayers and pſalmes: and the like
ſong in her owne hearing againſt all tyrannie by inuaſion of Gods enemies: and this euery man
may iudge to bee farre from any colour of <hi>mutinie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(<hi rend="sup">c</hi>) It was a meete occupation for a blinde man, to put lyes into ſongs: and if he knewe how
falſe his verſes were when he publiſhed them, it were to be wiſhed that hee had his eyes
reſtored to ſee his lyes, and then his tongue cutte out that vttered them, and his eyes cleane
plucked out of his head, that he ſhould neuer ſee any more written lyes. As for his eares, it
were good to haue them open, to heare men call him iuſtly, a notable blinde lyar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:18259:3"/>
               <head>A Condemnation of the <hi>Spaniſh lies.</hi> From England.</head>
               <p n="2">2 THe Gouernour of <hi>Roan</hi> is accompted a worthy noble man, and therefore he ſhall
do wel to make this report of him to bee kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen for a lie: for ſo ſurely he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it to be,
that there was neuer ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a chiefe Pilote or the value of a boy of Captaine <hi>Drakes</hi>
taken and brought to him as a priſoner.</p>
               <p>The Gouernours of <hi>Bollen</hi> and <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leis</hi> can informe the Gouernour of
<hi>Roan,</hi> how falſe a report it was, that the Engliſh Armie remained ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen afore
<hi>Calleis:</hi> the Engliſh armie fought with the Spaniſh, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Spaniſh as a brace
of Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds would a herde of Deere: the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſhips were beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſpoyled,
burnt, ſunke, ſome in the maine ſeas afore <hi>Dunkirke,</hi> ſome afore
<hi>Fluſhing,</hi> and the reſt chaſed away, ſo as they fledde continually afore the
Engliſh Nauie in their beſt order for ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, without daring to abide any fight: yea,
ſome one of the Engliſh ſhippes fought with 3. of their <hi>Galleaſſes,</hi> the
<hi>Spaniards</hi> neuer atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pting to board any Engliſh, but as many of them as coulde ſaile
away, fled with all their ſailes, &amp; were followed by the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, vntil they were chaſed
out of all the Engliſh ſeas, and forced then to runne a violent courſe about
<hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Ireland,</hi> where a great
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18259:4"/> number of their ſhips are drowned, their men taken, and many killed by the
ſauage people for their ſpoyle, and the Engliſh Nauie vpon good conſideration left them,
when they ſawe them ſo haſtily to flie deſperat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the Northren daungerous Seas, where
the Engliſh Nauie did very certainely know that there would be no ſafety for them to folow the
Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh. Why durſt any report that 22. Engliſh ſhippes were ſunke, and 40. were taken,
when in trueth there was not any one of the Engliſh ſhippes ſunke or taken? A ſtrange
diſpoſition, to forge ſuch great lyes, whereof there was no ground, nor colour. If any one or
two of the Engliſh had bene ſunke, a lyar might haue put the nomber of 20. for 2. and excuſed
the lye by error of figuring: but of none in nomber, no nomber can bee made, but by falſhood. The
Gouernour of <hi>Roan</hi> being a man of great honour and vertue, ought to reuenge this
ſhamefull lye made vpon him: for <hi>Lucian</hi> neuer did in all his lyes vſe more impudencie,
then theſe <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> lyars doe report of him.</p>
               <p>(<hi rend="sup">d</hi>) If <hi>Drakes</hi> ſhippe were taken, if there was ſuch a piece of ordinance of ſuch
a length, in what Port is that ſhippe? in whoſe poſſeſsion is that piece? <hi>Drake</hi>
is returned with honour: his ſhippe called the <hi>Reuenge</hi> is in harborow, ready for a
reuenge by a newe ſeruice, no ſhippe loſt, no ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance miſſing.</p>
               <p>(<hi rend="sup">e</hi>) The fooliſh lyar maketh mention of <hi>Abſpurg</hi> in Scotland: in all
<hi>Scotland</hi> is no ſuch place, in <hi>Germanie</hi> is a countrey called
<hi>Habſpurg,</hi> but any wager may be layd, that none of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> came euer
thither. Euery line, or euery ſentence, conteineth a lye.</p>
               <p>The Duke him ſelfe is returned: let him confirme this vntrueth, that he ouerthrewe the
Engliſh armie: it can not be imagined, that hee, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a perſon of ſo great honour) will
allow ſo notorious a lye to be taken for a trueth: for if he had ſuch a victorie, why did hee
not land to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere England? why did he neuer enter into any part of England? why did hee neuer
cary any Enſigne of England into <hi>Spaine</hi> to ſhew, as very many of the
<hi>Spaniſh</hi> were brought into Englande?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18259:4"/>
               <head>A condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> lies. <hi>From England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="3">3 ALl this is likewiſe as full of lyes, as lines. <hi>Iohn Gamarra</hi> may be what he
is: but if there be ſuch a man, and that hee wrote as is mentioned, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept hee bee a
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed member of the Deuill to forge lyes, hee knoweth that he wrote falſly.</p>
               <p>(<hi rend="sup">f</hi>) Hee noteth alſo a Hauen in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande</hi> called <hi>Luxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten:</hi> none ſuch was
euer knowen there. In <hi>Vtopia</hi> there may bee ſuch a one: no <hi>Spaniard</hi> can ſaye
that they tooke any Haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <hi>Scotland:</hi> it is altogether vaine otherwiſe to reproue this:
but al that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported are lyes, &amp; ſo let <hi>Gamarra</hi> repent, or follow the Deuill his
maſter, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:18259:5"/>
               <head>A condemnation of the <hi>Spaniſh lies.</hi> From England.</head>
               <p n="4">4 THis <hi>Pedro Alua</hi> coulde bee content to ſend lies, but he is more warie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
auowing of them: hee reporteth lyes, as hee ſaith, that came from other places. But of all other
places, none coulde make a truer report then <hi>Calleis,</hi> where the Gouernour, and all the
inhabitants ſaw the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> armie mightily bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Engliſh, and it was
affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by men there of great iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that neuer was ſeene by any man liuing ſuch a
battery, ſo great for nomber, ſo furious, and of ſo long continuance, as the Engliſh made
againſt the <hi>Spaniſh. Calleis</hi> ſawe the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> armie firſt driuen from
their ancres with fire: they ſawe the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>Galliaſſe</hi> of the
<hi>Spaniſh,</hi> whereof was Commander that worthy noble man <hi>Moncada,</hi> ſpoyled, &amp;
himſelfe ſlaine in the <hi>Galliaſſe</hi> by the Engliſh. <hi>Calleis</hi> did ſee the
next day, that the Engliſh Nauie fought and did beate the Spaniſh <hi>Armada</hi> from viii. of
the clocke in the Morning, vntill 4. in the afternone without any ceaſing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calleis</hi> ſawe the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> hoyſe vp al their ſayles, &amp; flie as
faſt as winde could driue, &amp; the Engliſh to follow and purſue them, and yet
<hi>Calleis</hi> ſaw a ſufficient Nauie of England left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Dunkirke,</hi> able to
maſter all the Shipping that the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> had prouided. (<hi rend="sup">g</hi>) The laſt part of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18259:5"/> this report is a like lye to the other: there is no ſuch Port in
<hi>Scotland,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Trifla,</hi> neither did any of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> take
ſuccour in any Hauen, nor yet could haue done, by reaſon of the contrary windes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A condemnation of the <hi>Spaniſh lies.</hi> From England.</head>
               <p n="5">5 HEre followeth the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of lies. It is reaſon that if there were lyars in
London, they ſhould ſend them to <hi>Mendoza:</hi> for ſo <hi>Mendacia</hi> are of more price
with him, then true reportes, and ſo was he accuſtomed when he was Ambaſſadour in Englande,
to buye more lyes, becauſe hee liked them, better then truethes.</p>
               <p>If one ſhould make a Section, or anatomie of this Mountaine and body of lyes, there is no
piece, nor ioynt to be found ſound. (<hi rend="sup">h</hi>) The Admirall Shippe, which was called the ARKE ROYALL,
was ſafely brought home by the Lord Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of England <hi>L. Howard:</hi> he neuer changed her,
ſhee is (thanked bee GOD) ſafe with other the Queenes Royal Shippes, ſhe is able with the
Lorde Admirall, to match in fight with the Duke of <hi>Medina,</hi> or any Prince of
Chriſtendome, in any ſhip that the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath. This
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18259:6"/> is not ſpoken for oſtentation: but Gods fauour is aſſured to Englande in
the Iuſtice of the quarell, againſt any Inuadour.</p>
               <p>(<hi rend="sup">i</hi>) If there were a <hi>mutinie</hi> of Catholikes, they ſhould haue bene hanged or
puniſhed: but it was not knowen that one Catholique did ſtir this Summer with hand or to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue to
mooue offence, neither was any one impriſoned, or otherwiſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
               <p>(<hi rend="sup">k</hi>) The laſt line is a lye, with like errour as the former: for there is no Hauen in
<hi>Scotland</hi> called <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pena Exaten.</hi> This <hi>Mendoza</hi> was very curious to forge
a ſtrange name, as it appeareth hee had read of ſome ſuch in <hi>Peru</hi> or in new
<hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A condemnation of the <hi>Spaniſh lies.</hi> From England.</head>
               <p n="6">6 THis <hi>Scottiſhman,</hi> (I thinke,) hath no name: a manifeſt lye it was, that
<hi>Scottiſhmen</hi> had taken Armes againſt the Engliſh. Such a lie did <hi>Mendoza</hi>
publiſh ſome yeres paſt, that the king of <hi>Scots</hi> had beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and wonne
<hi>Barwicke.</hi> I truſt he remembreth now, how falſe a lye it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18259:6"/> was: but yet he hath no grace, as it ſeemeth, to forbeare fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forging of
lyes, for his chollerike appetite. But a manifeſt trueth it is, that the King of <hi>Scots</hi>
at the time meant, made a generall Proclamation, that no <hi>Scottiſhman</hi> ſhould victuall
any <hi>Spaniard,</hi> for that the King did knowe they came to haue conquered both England and
Scotland. And on the other ſide, the King by Proclamation commaunded, that all ſuccours
ſhould be giuen to the Armie of England, as being the armie of his Siſter and confederate, and
the Prince whom he knew to be inuaded moſt iniuſtly. Many <hi>Scottiſhmen</hi> might at
<hi>Burdeaux</hi> haue reported this for a truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>of Spaniſh lies.</hi> From Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</head>
               <p n="7">7 AL theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true newes are ſayde to haue come from the ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Fleete, to the
Kings Maieſtie. By this tyme is it ſure, that the Duke of <hi>Medina</hi> can tell the King his
Maſter ſome other contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry matters: for elſe he had no cauſe to flie about Scotland and
Ireland. (<hi rend="sup">l</hi>) He alſo wil not ſay,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18259:7"/> that eyther three Galiaſſes, &amp; foure Galleo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land were ſunk,
or that euer hee coulde ſee one ſhip or one boat of England ſunk. He can tell the King with
great griefe, that hee neuer had fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate day, from his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming from the <hi>Groine,</hi> till he
returned with the loſſe of as many ſhippes, men, victuals, treaſure, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as
might haue made a good armie by ſea: and great pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie it is for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, that both that
which is loſt, and that which remaineth had not beene v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the King Catholik, againſt the
Infidels, and not with ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on to imploy ſuch kinde of forces, to inuade Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
countreys therewith, who
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18259:7"/> if he would liue in peace with them, would be readye to ioine their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
with his, to dilate the fines of Chriſtendome, &amp; forbeare ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Chriſtian blood
amongſt Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>(m) This Noble man was killed with a ſmal ſhot in the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſſe, where in very trueth
hee remayned in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſſe, and ſought not to flie away, as a great nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
did.</p>
               <p>(n) If it be meant, the xii. of Auguſt, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth is apparant: for there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fight
after that afore Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leis, which was the xxix. of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, <hi>Stilo antiquo,</hi> and the 8. of
their Auguſt.</p>
               <p>(o) It is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true, that the Spaniards ſhips
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18259:8"/> to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues light to flie, did caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their boates, they threw
their Moiles and horſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſeas.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A condemnation of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh lies. <hi>From England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="8">8 THis that is ſayd of the <hi>Dukes</hi> grapling with <hi>Drakes</hi> ſhip, and
taking of him captiue, and many other Noble men of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, is like all the reſt of the
lyes.</p>
               <p>The Duke after hee went from <hi>Calleis</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Scotland,</hi> neuer came neere to
offer fight with any <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhippe, neuer turned backe to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> that
followed him, but fledde away as winde and ſayle could ſerue him.</p>
               <p>If he had this fortune thus falſely reported, it is ſure that hee would haue brought both
<hi>Drake</hi> and ſome of the Noble men home with him into <hi>Spaine,</hi> to haue beene
preſented to the king, and not to haue gone home to his owne houſe without ſight of the
<hi>King.</hi> But in truth, there was not one Noble man, or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of any Marke that went to
the ſea, that was either ſlaine or taken: all are liuing, and are as willing, by Gods fauour,
to aduenture their liues, as euer they were againſt any of the Queens enemies, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe ſhal
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand them.</p>
               <p>And where theſe newes did much content the <hi>King,</hi> it is likely that if he thought them
true, he was glad thereof, for ſo had his Maieſtie cauſe: but hee is thought too wiſe, to
haue
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18259:8"/> thought, that after hee vnderſtoode that the Duke and all his armie had fled
from the coaſt of <hi>Flanders</hi> &amp; <hi>England,</hi> that euer they were like to haue any
victorie of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> No, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe the King and all his wiſe Counſellours
had cauſe to lament the dangers, whereunto of neceſſitie his <hi>Armada</hi> ſhould fall by
paſſing the dangerous coaſtes, Ilandes, &amp; monſtruous rockes of <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp;
<hi>Ireland,</hi> of more danger for his Nauie to paſſe, then to haue paſſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <hi>Lisborne</hi> to the <hi>Moloccas,</hi> and home againe.</p>
               <p>It is to be thought, that if the Empreſſe gaue the ſecretarie <hi>Ydiaques</hi> any
rewarde for the newes, as it is likely ſhee did: ſhe may iuſtly require it againe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him,
and giue him charge not to bring her Maieſtie, nor the King his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter any ſuch notorious
lyes hereafter: for if he vſe it often, he is vnworthie to be Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie to ſo great a
King.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="colophon">
               <p>
                  <hi>Jmprinted at London by the</hi> DEPVTIES of Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Barker, Printer to the QVEENES
moſt excellent Maieſtie. 1588.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="epigraph">
               <q>
                  <bibl>ZACH. 8.26.</bibl>
                  <p>Theſe are the things that ye ſhall doe: Speake ye euery man the trueth vnto his
neighbour.</p>
                  <bibl>EPHES. 4.25.</bibl>
                  <p>Wherefore caſt off lying, and ſpeake euery man trueth vnto his neighbour: for we are
mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers one of another.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
